Phil: Welcome to the first unit! This is the unit where you get the “big picture,”
and a first few details.
Nick :You’re going to learn the basics of how the Internet works. You might even figure
out which one of us is Phil and which one is Nick. We hope to help you to understand
*why* the Internet is designed the way it is. What are some of its strengths and weaknesses?
We’ll also teach you some of the commonly accepted network design principles, such as
layering, encapsulation, and packet switching. At the end of this unit, you should be able
to answer questions such as “What is the Internet? What is an Internet Address?”
and “How do applications such as the web, Skype, and BitTorrent work?” These principles
will help you design better networks in the future.
Phil: At the end of the first unit, you should be familiar with something called the “4-layer
model” of the Internet. It describes how the Internet is broken down into four distinct
layers. You’ll learn what layers are and why they’re a basic principle of good network
design. You’ll learn what the Internet’s four layers are and how they work together.
You’ll learn that most applications use a transport layer called the Transmission
Control Protocol, or TCP, and how some applications use it.
You’ll also learn that the Internet works by breaking data up into small units called
packets. For example, when you request a web page, your computer sends some packets to
the web server. The Internet decides how these packets of data arrive to the right destination.
Nick: This unit also examines one layer, called the network layer, in a bit of detail. You
might have heard of IP, the Internet Protocol. It’s the protocol named after the Internet
because it’s the glue that lets the whole thing work. You can change all of the other
layers, but to be using the Internet you need to be using the Internet Protocol at the network
layer. You’ll learn about what the Internet Protocol does and how it does it. You’ll
learn about Internet Protocol addresses and how they’re assigned. You’ll start to
learn how the Internet decides the path a packet should take based on Internet addresses.
Phil: Finally, we’ll show you a few software tools you can use to inspect how your computer
is using the Internet. So you can apply what you’ve learned in this unit to the next
time you browse the web!