In this unit, learned some of the basics about how the Internet works. You learned how applications
like web browsing and Skype work, how an application use the Internet, and the basic structure
of the Internet. You learned about some of the fundamental architectural principles of
networking. Perhaps by now you know which one of us is Phil and which one is Nick.
Now you’ve finished the first unit, you should be very familiar with this picture
of the 4-layer model of the Internet. You now know that the Internet is broken down
into four distinct layers, what the four layers are, and how they work together. But even
more importantly than how it works, you hopefully understand why it works this way and why layering
is a good idea in all networks, not just the Internet.
You’ve now seen that the Internet works by breaking data up into small units called
packets. When you request a web page, your computer sends some packets to the web server.
The Internet decides how these little pieces of data arrive to the right destination – and
how the packets the web server responds with, containing the page, make their way to you
correctly as well.
You‘ve learned how two architectural principles, layering and packets, come together, in the
architectural principle of encapsulation. Encapsulation is how one takes layers and
lets them use packets in a clean and simple way, such that each layer’s use of a packet
is independent of the others. We’ll talk about a few more architectural principles
in later units.
In this unit we studied four main topics
1. How an application uses the Internet. Phil explained the common way in which a variety
of different applications use the Internet, using Skype, BitTorrent and the Web as specific
examples. You learned that most applications want to communicate over a reliable, bi-directional
byte-stream between two or more end points.
2. The structure of the Internet. You learnd what the 4-layer model is, and the responsibility
of each layer. You also learned why we use the Internet Protocol or “IP” every time
we send packets across the Internet, and why we call IP the “thin waist” of the Internet.
3. The Internet protocol (IP). Because IP is so important, we spent several videos describing
what IP does for us, and how it works. So far we’ve focussed on IP version 4, because
it’s the most widely used version of IP today. You’ll learn about IP addresses,
how routers look up IP addresses and so on. Later in the course you’ll learn about the
newer version of IP, IPv6.
4. Basic architectural ideas and principles. You’ve studied three fundamental principles
of networks, all of which are very relevant to our understanding of the Internet. The
first is packet switching, which is the simple way in which data is broken down into self-contained
packets of information that are forwarded hop-by-hop based on the information in the
packet header. The second is Layering, which we’ve already mentioned. And the third is
encapsulation, which is the process of placing a packet processed at one layer inside the
data of the packet below. This helps a clear separation of concerns between how data is
processed at each layer in the hierarchy.
you should now have a good understanding of the basic structure of the Internet and three
basic architectural ideas. You understand how applications like your web browser works,
and how the Internet delivers packets between two computers. You‘d probably heard the
term TCP/IP used before: now you know what TCP is and what IP is, and why they’re related.
At first glance, these might seem like grungy, low-level details. But it turns out that they’re
the bedrock of what the Internet is. Every year, new applications and uses of the Internet
emerge. But all of them use these basic principles you’re learning about, and almost all of
them use TCP/IP. By starting with these fundamentals that have remained amazingly constant, you’ll
learn the knowledge that will continue to be important even as we move on to 5G wireless
networks, Web 3.0, and the Internet of Things.
And that’s part of what’s exciting. The Internet and what it can do is always expanding
and changing. But there are some core ideas and principles which are constant through
all of that evolution. By learning them, you not only know how the Internet and networks
work today, but most likely how they will work in 20 years as well.