The Internet Protocol allows two computers to exchange messages across a network that&#39;s
built out of many different link layers. It does so through addresses. An IP packet has
a source and a destination address. Routers decide which link to forward a packet over
based on the packet&#39;s destination address. Let’s look in detail at what IP version
4 addresses look like, how they are formatted, and how they are allocated.
The original goal of the Internet Protocol was to take many different networks and stitch
them together. For this to work, the protocol needed a way to refer to a computer that was
independent of the network it was on and unique. So a computer on an IBM network and a computer
connected to a router over a serial line can talk to each other, and need a way to address
each other. Today, IPv4 addresses are a bit more complicated, they’re not totally unique
due to a bunch of special cases and uses, but for now let’s just assume they’re
unique.
An Internet Protocol, version 4 address is 32 bits long. This 32 bits is often written
as 4 octets, 4 8 bit values, in the form a.b.c.d. Here are three examples. 171.64.64.64, 128.30.76.82,
and 12.22.58.30. Every device connected through IPv4 has an IP address. The IP layer delivers
packets whose destination is this address to that device.
In addition to an address, a device typically also has something called a netmask. A netmask
tells the device which IP addresses are local -- on the same link -- and which require going
through an IP router. Think, for example, of a laptop on a wireless network. In order
to send a packet to another device in the same wireless network, the laptop doesn’t
need to go through an IP router. It can, in theory, just send the packet directly to the
other device since it’s on the same link.
A netmask is written as a string of consecutive 1s, starting with the most significant bit.
A netmask of 255.255.255.0, for example, means the first 3 octets are all 1s (2 to the 8th
-1 is 255) and the last octet is zero. This means that an IP address which matches the
first three octets -- 24 bits -- of your IP address is in the same network. A netmask
of 255.255.252.0 means the netmask is 22 bits long, while 255.128.0.0 is a 9 bit netmask.
You tell whether two computers are in the same network by taking a bitwise AND of their
addresses with the netmask. If the resulting addresses are equal, they are in the same
network.
Let’s see what this looks like on my computer. I can open up a terminal an use the ifconfig
program. My computer is connected to the Internet over WiFi, which happens to be the link named
“en1.” If we look inside the “en1” information, we can see that my Internet Protocol
version 4 address is 192.168.0.106 and my netmask is 0xffffff00, which is hexidecimal
for 255.255.255.0. This means that if I send an IP packet to an address beginning with
192.168.0 I should send it directly, but if it doesn’t begin with 192.168.0 I need to
send it through a router.