For two parties to communicate, they need to agree on the messages they exchange. If
one party assumes messages are in Spanish and the other assumes they are in Cambodian,
they will not be able to communicate. For computer communication, this means agreeing
on what fields messages have, how they are arranged and formatted, and how they are represented.
To generate a message to send, software typically has to create a copy of it in memory, which
it then passes to the networking card. Similarly, when a computer receives a message, the networking
card puts that message in memory, which software can then access. Understanding how this works
and some of the pitfalls you can encounter is important if you want to understand network
protocols and write network protocol software. So let’s start with a simple model of computer
memory. In most computers today, memory is organized in terms of bytes: 8 bit chunks
of memory. A program has an address space, starting at address zero. Most computers today
are 64 bits: this means that memory addresses are 64 bits long, so a computer has up to
2 to the 64 bytes, or 18 sextillion bytes. In practice, computers today do not have this
much memory: they have gigabytes, which is 2 to the 30th. In this example, our computer
has 8 gigabytes of memory, so its largest address is the hexidecimal value shown. Software
can access each byte of this memory, or access bytes in groups, such as loading a 64-bit
integer from 8 contiguous byte cells of memory in a single instruction. But how does a computer
represent a multibyte value? Let’s say we want to represent the number 1,024, which
in hexidecimal is 0x0400, or 4 times 256. This value requires 16 bits, or two bytes.
Which byte comes first: 0x00 or 0x04? How you lay out a multibyte value in memory is
called endianness, and there are two options. In little endian, the least significant byte
is at the lowest address. So the least significant byte comes first in memory. It turns out that
from a computational and architectural standpoint, this can make the most sense. The other option
is big endian, where the most significant byte is the lowest address. Big endian makes
more sense to a human reader, because it’s how we write numbers, with the most significant
digits first.