Phil: When the Internet was designed, it was based on a controversial and revolutionary
idea: packet switching. Nowadays it seems straightforward and the obvious way to build
networks. But that wasn’t always the case. It’s a very simple idea, but of course as
it is with simple ideas, there are many interesting implications that arise once you put it into
practice. We’ll spend an entire week of the course on packet switching and its implications,
but in this video we present the high-level idea and its immediate benefits.
Nick
Packet: A self-contained unit of data that carries information necessary for it to reach
its destination.
Packet switching is the idea that we break our data up into discrete, self-contained
chunks of data. Each chunk, called a packet, carries sufficient information that a network
can deliver the packet to its destination. So let’s say we have a source and a destination,
and a network of packet switches A, B, and C between them. When A receives a packet for
the destination, it sends it along the link to B. When B receives a packet for the destination,
it sends it along to C. When C receives a packet for the destination, it sends it to
the destination. In the simplest form of packet switching, each packet is routed separately
and independently. For example, let’s say there’s another switch connected to B, called
D. Immediately after sending a packet to C, B can send the next packet to D. Or, if the
next packet were also to the destination, it would send two packets back-to-back to
C.
Packet switching: Independently for each arriving packet, pick its outgoing link. If the link
is free, send it. Else hold the packet for later.
Here’s one example of how packet switching can work: each packet contains an explicit
route, specifying the IDs of each packet switch along the way. We call this “self routing”
or “source routing,” because the source specifies the route. When the source sends
a packet, it puts in the packet A, B, C, destination. It then forwards the packet to A. A looks
inside the header and sees the next hop is B. So it forwards the packet to B. B sees
the next hop is C, and C sees the last hop is the destination. It turns out the Internet
supports source routing, but it’s generally turned off because it raises big security
issues. People owning routers don’t want you telling them how to send packets, because
maybe you can trick them to sending them somewhere they shouldn’t, such as secure computers.
One simple optimization, and what the Internet mostly does today, is to place a small amount
of state in each switch which tells it which next hop to send packets to. For example,
a switch can have a table of destination addresses and the next hop. When it receives a packet,
it looks up the address in the table, and sends the packet to the appropriate next hop.
In this model, all the packet needs to carry is the destination address. Using the address,
each switch along the way can make the right decision. For example, in our network here,
A’s table says that packets to destination should go to switch B, switch B’s table
says packets to destination should go to switch C, and so on.
In packet switching, there is no dedicated circuit to carry our data. Instead, we send
a block of data by adding a header to it, and call it a packet. The header contains
the address of where the packet is going, just like an envelope tells the post office
where to send a letter. &lt;click to send packet on link&gt; A packet switched
network consists of end-hosts, links, and packet switches. When we send a packet, it
is routed hop-by-hop to its destination. Each packet switch lookups the address in the packet
header in its local forwarding table. For example, this packet is addressed to B.
When we transmit it, the first router looks up address B in its local table, and sees
that switch S2 is the next hop. S2 and S4 do the same thing, and the packet is eventually
delivered to B.In the Internet there are several different types of packet switches. Some of
them are called routers or gateways, while others are called Ethernet switches. We’ll
learn more about each of them later. At this stage you just need to know that they are
both types of packet switch, and they forward packets based on the destination address in
the header.
Packet switching has two really nice properties. The first is that a switch can make individual,
local decisions for each packet. It doesn’t need to keep extra state on the packets its
seen or whether two packets go to the same destination. Even if many packets are part
of some larger transfer or protocol, the switch doesn’t need to know or care. The switch
doesn’t need to know that some packets are a Skype call, others are a web request, and
others still are a firmware update for your computer. It just forwards packets. This greatly
simplifies the switch.
The second is that it lets a switch efficiently share a link between many parties. For example,
consider a wireless router in a home with two people browsing the Internet on their
laptops. (Draw picture) If one person is reading a page, then the other person can download
a file at the full speed of the link. If the first person starts loading a new web page,
the link can be shared between the two of them. Once the download completes, the first
person can use the full speed of the link.
These two points are really important, so we’ll go into some greater detail on both
of them.
Nick: Of course when we communicate we don’t usually send only one packet, we send many;
for example a voice call consists of many consecutive packets all part of the same communication.
We call this sequence of packets a flow. More specifically:
Flow: A collection of datagrams belonging to the same end-to-end communication, e.g.
a TCP connection.
Let’s first look at each packet being routed independently.
Because each packet is self-contained, a switch doesn’t need to know about groups of packets,
or flows of packets. Imagine if every switch had to keep track of every single web connection
passing through it. This would require a huge amount of state that would be hard to manage!
Instead, treating each packet independently means the switch can be much simpler to build,
manage, and troubleshoot.
The switch doesn’t need to worry about adding or removing this per-flow state. Imagine if
every time you wanted to load a web page, you had to communicate with every switch along
the path to set up state so your request would work. This could make things much slower.
Instead, you can just send packets and the switches forward them appropriately.
The switches also don’t need to *store* this state. Because switches have to be fast,
they’d need to store this state in very fast memory, which is expensive. This lets
switches focus on doing one thing, forwarding packets quickly.
Finally, it means switches don’t have to worry about failures. Imagine, for example,
what happens when you start a web request but then your tablet runs out of energy. The
switch is going to keep the per-flow state for the request, but if one of the nodes that
created the state fails, the switch needs to know how to clean up after it. Otherwise
you can have millions, billions of dead flows eating up your memory. With packet switching,
a switch has no per-endpoint state. If your tablet dies, the switch doesn’t care, it
just means that it stops receiving packets from it. In this way the switch is more functionally
independent of the computers sending traffic through it.
Phil
Think about how you typically use the Internet – your use is bursty. You load a web page,
then read it, then load another one. You download a few songs from iTunes, then listen to them.
You stream a show from Netflix for forty five minutes, then stop. Data traffic is bursty:
rather than always sending and receiving data at a fixed rate, usage jumps and drops, goes
up and down, over time.
While there are large-scale changes and peaks in data traffic – 3PM is typically high,
as is 8PM, while 2AM is low, on a smaller scale it is very bursty and these bursts are
often independent. Let’s say you and your friend are both browsing the web in a coffee
shop. When you load a new page and when your friend loads a new page are mostly independent.
Sometimes they might overlap, but often they won’t. By treating all of your traffic as
just packets, the wireless router can very effectively and simply share its capacity
between you. If you’re loading a page while your friend is reading, the wireless router
can give all of its capacity to your packets. Similarly, if your friend is loading a page
and you’re reading, the router can give all of its capacity to your friend’s packets.
The link doesn’t need to go partially idle because one of you isn’t using it, and if
you’re both using it then the link can be shared between you.
This idea of taking a single resource and sharing it across multiple users in a probabilistic
or statistical way is called statistical multiplexing. It’s statistical in that each user receives
a statistical share of the resource based on how much others are using it. For example,
if your friend is reading, you can use all of the link. If both of you are loading a
page, you receive half of the link capacity.
Nick: So those are the two major benefits of packet switching: it makes the switches
simple because they don’t need to know about flows of packets. And second, it lets us efficiently
share the capacity among many flows sharing a link. This simple building block was revolutionary
at the time, but it’s now accepted as the common way to build networks.