Nick: In the last few videos you’ve seen many references to “layering”, particularly
in the video describing the 4-layer Internet Model. Layering is a very widely used principle
and has been used in networking for decades, predating the Internet.
In fact, layering is a design principle used widely outside networking as well --- it is
commonly used as a design principle in many many types of computer system. There are lots
of reasons for layering, and we’ll explore some of them in this video. We’ll explore
what layering is, we’ll look at some simple examples of layering in communication and
computer systems, and we’ll explain why so many systems are layered – either by
natural happenstance or deliberately by design.
Let’s start with a definition of layering.
Layering is the name we give to the organization of a system into a number of separate functional
components, or layers.
The layers are hierarchical and they communicate sequentially; i.e. each layer has an interface
only to the layer directly above or below.
Each layer provides a well defined service to the layer above, using the services provided
by the layer(s) below and its own private processing.
There are many examples of layering in everyday life, particularly when one service is deliberately
or naturally layered on top of another. For example, if you are looking for airplane tickets
you might visit a brokerage website such as Google Flights, Hipmunk or Kayak. These websites
let you find tickets across a wide range of airlines by communicating with a single service.
You could, instead, go to the website of every airline to query what tickets they have available.
A brokerage website provides a service layer on top of each airline, abstracting away the
details of each airline’s website for you. Now, if we look under the covers of each airline,
they fly different types of airplane, over different routes. The airline takes care of
the details of providing the service, and offers you the simple abstraction of a ticket
valid for a particular flight to take you between two airports. They hide many other
details too, such as how they provide the awful food they serve. In most cases, they
have a number of suppliers to provide meals, drinks, fuel and so on. Each of those are
naturally hidden from us, the consumer. This separation of concerns allows each layer in
the hierarchy to focus on doing its job well, and provide a well defined service to the
layer above.
Another well known example of layering, closer to the Internet, is the postal service.
Imagine that I have a book that I want to send to Phil &lt;click for book to appear then
arrow to appear&gt;
I place it in an envelope, add Phil’s address and mine and then hand it to Olive to take
to the mailbox. The postal service sorts the mail, then sends
it by a variety of different means (airplanes, mail trucks, trains etc) until it reaches
a sorting office near Phil. The mail man delivers the letter to Phil, who opens it and finds
the book inside.
The service is layered. At the top, I don’t care how the letter gets from me to Phil – whether
it goes by plane, truck or hovercraft. And I don’t care about the route it takes, or
how many sorting offices it passes through along the way. I don’t mind whether Olive
walks, skips, bicycles or runs to the mailbox; I don’t care which mailbox she posts the
letter in. I want the lower layers to abstract away the details for me, providing me with
a simple service model. I put the book in an envelope and the layers below deliver it
to Phil. In turn, Olive doesn’t need to know how the postal service delivers the letter;
she simply communicates with the layer below by posting the letter. Phil just wants the
book.
Notice that each layer communicates only with the layers above and below. If the postal
service deploys new trains, or starts using a different airline freight service, Phil
and I don’t need to know about it. IN other words, because communication is simply up
and down, with a well defined interface between layers, we can improve each layer independently
over time. For example, if I want faster, guaranteed delivery, I could hand the envelope
to a carrier such as DHL or Fedex. The interface is almost the same – I give them an envelope
and money.
Phil: Layering is deliberately designed into many computer systems.
When we write programs – this is TY editing a program – we create source code using
a language that abstracts away the details of the operating system, how virtual memory
works, and the low level details of the hardware. (OK, so C isn’t great at hiding the details
– but many other languages, like Java and Python deliberately shield us from how the
lower layers work).
As a programmer we communicate with the layer below – the compiler – by handing it our
source code. The compiler is a self-contained functional component that is responsible for
several tasks, such as: lexical analysis, parsing our code, preprocessing declarations,
and then code generation and optimization. The compiler generates object code, which
is then passes to the linker.
The linker links together the compiled object files and libraries. It generates an executable
file.
The CPU (real or virtual) then executes the code.
If you have experience writing computer programs, the benefits of layering are fairly clear
in this example. Layering breaks down the overall problem of writing programs that execute
on hardware into modules, or functional components, each with a well defined role and providing
a well defined service to the layer above. It also provides a clear separation of concerns:
The compiler can focus on lexical analysis, parsing and so on; the linker can focus on
efficiently piecing objects together. Neither has to worry about the job of the other, and
each can be improved, upgraded and replaced over time as technology and know-how progress.
For example, we might swap out a commercial C compiler with “gcc” or vice-versa, without
needing to change the linker or the language we use.
When Nick first drafted these slides, I was excited that he put compilers in as an example
of layering: they’re a great example of both the benefits of layering as well as how
sometimes you need to break layering despite its very negative consequences.
Let’s take the C programming language as an example. Generally speaking, a piece of
C code can be compiled for almost any processor. We can take C code like i++ and compile it
for an ARM processor in a phone, an x86_64 processor in a laptop, or microcontroller
in an ultra-modern dish washer. In this way the C code is hardware independent and so
keeps the layering here.
But sometimes we need our C code to do something special that only our processor can do. For
example, an x86_64 processor has all kinds of special instructions that a microcontroller
doesn’t. C allows you to directly include assembly code. Software like operating systems
kernels such as Linux and Windows use this for some of their lowest level implementations.
The layering that C provides hides this detail so doesn’t let you do so directly, but you
have to do it to achieve your goal. So OS kernels include assembly code. Doing this
means that code is no longer layer independent: the Linux context switch assembly written
for ARM only works for ARM. So you have to write a version for each layer. If Linux wants
to run on a new processor, developers need to write new assembly code for that processor.
So this is a great example because it shows the benefits of layers they separate concerns
and simplify your system, just as programming C is easier than assembly. But sometimes you
have to break the layer boundaries. Doing so has a huge cost, suddenly you are no longer
independent of the lower layer, greatly limiting flexibility. So sometimes you have to do it,
but do so only when you really have to. As we’ll see, a lot of the practical, operational
challenges in the Internet today result from people breaking layering and assuming thinks
above and below their service interface: there’s a continual tension to improve the Internet
by making cross-layer optimizations and the resulting loss of flexibility. We’ll see
one really telling example of this with something called NATs, or Network Address Translators,
tremendously useful devices that have unfortunately made it almost impossible to add new transport
protocols to the Internet.
So in summary, there are five main reasons we use layering in computer systems:
Modularity: It breaks down the system into smaller, more manageable modules.
Well defined service: Each layer provides a well defined service to the layer above.
Reuse: A layer above can rely on all the hard work put in by others to implement the layers
below. It saves us the time to rewrite each layer whenever we build a system.
Separation of concerns: Each layer can focus on its own job, without having to worry about
how other layers do theirs. The only communication is up-down the layers, so it helps keep one
layer’s processing and data local and internal where possible, minimizing the complex interactions
between layers.
Continuous improvement:
A 6th benefit is specific to layered communication systems, such as the Internet. That is peer
to peer communications. In the 4-layer Internet model we saw how each layer communicates with
its peer on another system, using the delivery service provided by the layers below. Similarly,
in the mail example, Phil and I are communicating with each other as users, without worrying
about how the communication service works.