Internet routers can have many links. They have many options for which direction to forward
a received packet. To select which link to forward a packet over, routers today typically
use an algorithm called Longest Prefix Match.
In this example a client wants to open a TCP connection to a server on port 80, the typical
port for web servers. The packets to set up the connection and transfer data take many
hops between the client and server. On each hop of each packet, a router decides which
link to forward the packet over.
How does a router make this decision? It does so through something called a forwarding table,
shown here on the right. A forwarding table consists of a set of partial IP addresses.
The x’s show that the addresses are partial. The x’s represent wildcards. For example,
the second entry, reading 171.33.x.x means “any IP address whose first byte is 171
and whose second byte is 33.” This particular entry, for example, includes 171.33.5.245
as well as 171.33.1.1.
When a packet arrives, the router checks which forwarding table entry best matches the packet
and forwards the packet along the link associated with that forwarding table entry. By “best”,
I mean most specific. The default route is effectively all wildcards -- it matches every
IP address. If, when a packet arrives, there isn’t a more specific route than the default
route, the router will just use the default one.
Longest prefix match, or LPM, is the algorithm IP routers use to decide how to forward a
packet. Every router has a forwarding table. Entries in this forwarding table have two
parts: a CIDR entry describing a block of addresses, and a next hop for packets that
match that CIDR entry. An address might belong to multiple CIDR entries.
For example, in this routing table on the right, there are two entries, one for the
default route, which has a prefix of length 0, and one for 171.33.0.0/16. By default,
all packets will go over link 1. However, if the first 16 bits, two octets, of a packet
destination address matches 171.33, the router will send it over link 5. This is because
a 16 bit prefix is a longer prefix than 0 bits, it’s more specific.
So let’s go back to our earlier example, where we showed a forwarding table with Xs
denoting wildcards. Here’s the router and its forwarding table.
If we represent this forwarding table as CIDR entries, this is what it looks like. Since
in this simple example all of the prefixes are in terms of bytes, all of the prefixes
have length 0, 8, 16, or 24 bits.